Kheel, Theodore W. Subject Files 6021/007
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Theodore W. Kheel Subject Files
1971-1995
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Kheel, Theodore W.
6021/007
3.5 cubic feet
3.5 linear ft.
Records.
8240877
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, May 01, 2014
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, August 13, 2015
Biographical / Historical
Theodore Woodrow Kheel was said to be named for both Woodrow Wilson and his political rival Theodore Roosevelt, the result of a compromise between his politically differing parents. The settlement presaged a career in which Kheel would be tapped by mayors, governors, and presidents to settle disputes that were part of the nation's major political and social transitions from post-World War II to well into the 21st century.
Born in 1914 in Brooklyn, Ted Kheel attended public high school in the Bronx. He was awarded a Regents scholarship to Cornell University, where he attended an accelerated undergraduate law school program permitting him to earn a bachelor's and law degree in six years.
In private practice for a brief time after graduation from law school, Kheel soon was offered a position as a National Labor Relations Board attorney in Washington. Kheel's special talents as a mediator and his obvious political skills soon gave him the opportunity to move to a new war-time agency, where he was initially hired as principal mediation officer. By 1944, he had been appointed executive director of the National War Labor Board, with a staff of 2,500 who were hearing 150 disputes a week. Kheel's work at the WLB introduced him to the most important figures in the labor movement and key government officialscontacts he would use effectively in the future.
Following the end of World War II, Kheel returned to New York City and was drafted by Mayor O'Dywer to serve in the city's new Labor Relations Division, which Kheel came to head within a year. With the agreement of the mayor, Kheel was able to serve both in this position and maintain a separate, private law practice.
In 1949, Kheel was appointed to a part-time position as impartial chairman for an important segment of public transit in New York City, a position in which he would render 30,000 decisions through 1982. Also in 1949, Kheel became a partner in the New York law firm Battle, Fowler, Jaffin and Kheel. His skills in conflict resolution led an observer to remark that the firm's work began with a battle, ended by Kheel.
During his more than half a century of involvement in labor matters, Kheel was known above all else for his extraordinary ability to get feuding parties to make concessions to reach an agreement. In the important New York and national labor disputes which he would be called to mediate, Kheel's approach was to protect management rights and at the same time demand fairness to workers while also trying to protect the public interest in the issue.
Kheel's was frequently the voice of reason in settling a number of extremely difficult labor disputes of the 1960s and 1970s. Mayor Robert F. Wagner, Jr., turned to Kheel to help end the 114-day newspaper strike of 1962-63. Among his most infamous cases was the strike involving Mike Quill, head of the Transport Workers Union, who publically battled Mayor John V. Lindsay in 1965-66. Kheel's efforts also included helping coordinate bargainers and mediators during the 35-day New York City teachers' strike in 1968. President Lyndon B. Johnson summoned Kheel to Washington in 1964 to help mediate 10 days of feverish negotiations that prevented a nationwide rail walkout. Kheel would ultimately serve as a mediator and advisor for virtually every New York mayor from O'Dwyer to Beame, for the Kennedy-Johnson Administration, and other presidential administrations as well.
Kheel's interests in public issues were not limited to the labor sector. The policy disputes that came to his attention as a mediator and lawyer frequently cried out for larger solutions, and Kheel was not averse to using his considerable public presence and media contacts to seek redress, especially for what he viewed as past institutional injustices or misguided government actions. Although pressed to do so on a number of occasions, Kheel refused to run for elective office, preferring the role of a labor neutral and public advocate.
Kheel was also not averse to backing his powers of persuasion with legal action: a fierce advocate for public transit, he initiated a class action lawsuit over the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey's refusal to fund mass rail transit. His most sustained crusade for the public good related to his battle to limit commuter auto traffic and control highway building in New York City in favor of increased use of public transportation. Initially attacked by Port Authority officials and some city, state, and federal politicians of both parties, many of the solutions originally proposed by Kheel, including the concept of the subsidized fare, became public policy in later years.
An early supporter of the civil rights movement, Kheel and his wife Ann become involved with the New York Urban League in the 1950s. He served as its president in 1955 and as national president for four years. He worked with President Johnson on race issues and with Martin Luther King, Jr., in a libel suit against the New York Times. Kheel's mediation skills led to important strides in hiring African Americans in the airline industry. His reputation for sensitivity to minority issues resulted in his becoming involved in efforts to add civilians to the New York City Police Review Board in 1965. Kheel was also recruited as a peacemaker in the 1968 Ocean Hill-Brownsville Teachers dispute.
Even though Kheel handled disputes for transit workers, typesetters, and longshoremen, he reveled in the finer things in life, and dabbled as a restaurateur in fine food and was a patron of the fine arts.
He once owned a stake in Le Pavillon, a leading French restaurant in Manhattan, among others. He also represented numerous artists, including Robert Rauschenberg and Christo, and was the prime mover in the realization of the long-heralded Gates Project in Central Park in 2005.
He also made millions of dollars as an entrepreneur while facilitating sustainable economic and social change. He was the lead investor in the giant Punta Cana resort, transforming 30 miles of jungle in the Dominican Republic, and helped bring about the airport that opened that country to tourists and travelers.
Finding the solution to problems such as the impact of automation on the workplace, community disputes, and protecting a sustainable environment in which mankind will flourish, to name but a few, were the focus of Kheel's interest, enthusiasm, and financial support. He was the prime mover, bringing along like-minded citizens and specialists, in the creation of organizations to find solutions to the more intractable issues facing society. The Foundation on Employee Health, Medical Care and Welfare, the Foundation on Automation and Employment (and its British counterpart), Automation House, the Institute for Mediation and Conflict Resolution, and the Earth Pledge Foundation were among the most successful of such efforts. In the same vein, in collaboration with Price, Waterhouse in 1994, Kheel formed Prevention and Early Resolution of Conflicts, Inc. (PERC), now housed at Cornell ILR as Cornell/PERC Institute.
A prolific writer, Kheel is perhaps best known for his encyclopedic work on labor law. Throughout a career that was active almost until his death at age 96 in November 2010, he was able to balance, with amazing success, advocacy of the public good and the management of a successful law and mediation practice and other business and cultural interests.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5024: Theodore W. Kheel Arbitration Awards 5776 AV: Theodore W. Kheel Interviews and Programs 6017: Theodore W. Kheel Newspaper Clipping File 6021 AV: Theodore W. Kheel Audio-Visual Materials 6021 MB: Theodore W. Kheel Memorabilia 6021 P: Theodore W. Kheel Photographs 6021/001: Theodore W. Kheel Correspondence 6021/003: Theodore W. Kheel Arbitration files 6021/004: Theodore W. Kheel Legal Files 6021/005: Theodore W. Kheel Speeches and Articles 6021/006: Theodore W. Kheel Non-Profit Organization Files 6021/008: Theodore W. Kheel Books and Articles 6021/010: Theodore W. Kheel Additional Files 6021/011: Theodore W. Kheel Punta Cana Files 6021/012m: Invitation and Program for the Theodore W. Kheel Memorial Service 6059 OH: Thomas Shactman Interviews with Theodore W. Kheel 6194 OH: College of Labor and Employment Lawyers Interview with Theodore W. Kheel 6196 OH: New York City Central Labor Council Interview of Theodore W. Kheel for Central Archives 6207 OH: CLEL Video Oral History Project
Collective labor agreements; Kheel, Theodore Woodrow
8240877
- American Bank and Trust Co., 1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Collective Bargaining in Higher Education., 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Collective Bargaining Forum, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Collective Bargaining Forum, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Collective Bargaining Forum, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Collective Bargaining Forum, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- The Collective Bargaining Forum, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Scope and Contents
  May 12 - 13 1969
- Collective Bargaining Forum. Theodore Kheel Speech., 1970 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- The Collective Bargaining Forum, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Democratic Party, 1978-1982 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Federation of International Civil Servants' Association Council, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Federation of International Civil Servants' Association. Yearly Organizing Reunion of International Civil Services., 1994 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Federation of International Civil Servants' Association. Les Functionnaires Internationaux, 1993-1995 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Felissimo Tribute 21, Rauschenberg Project, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Returned to Mr. Kheel by UPS on July 16 2009
- Felissimo Tribute 21, Art Project Agreement, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Felissimo Tribute 21, Draft Agreements, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Felissimo Tribute 21, Ruder Finn Presentation, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Felissimo Design 21, UN Project, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Kheel Towers, 1979-1982 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Charles Robb, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Taylor Law, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  February 23 1968
- Report to Speaker Anthony J Travia on the Taylor Law, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  February 21 1968. Folder 1.
- Taylor Law. Public Employee Relations. Report to Anthony Travia on the Taylor Law from Kheel, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  February 21 1968. Folder 2.
- Taylor Public Employee Relations 83-A9. Miscellaneous, 1967-1969 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Taylor Law 83-A11. Newspaper Clippings., 1969 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Taylor Law 83-A12. Points for Consideration., 1968 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Taylor Law. Public Employee Relations. Governor's Conference, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  October 14 - 16 1968
- Taylor Law. Public Employee Relations. Taylor Recommendations to Rockefeller, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  January 23 1969
- Taylor Law. Public Employee Relations. Kheel Remarks, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  February 17 1969
- Taylor Report, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Taylor Law. Dispute, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Taylor Law. Original Draft of Summary., 1968 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Taylor Law. Public Employee Relations. Correspondence., 1967-1971 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Taylor Law. Public Employee Relations. Statute., 1967 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Taylor Law. Public Employee Relations. Guides., 1967-1970 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Taylor Law. Public Employee Relations. Summary Statement by Kheel., 1968 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Taylor Law. Public Employee Relations. Outline, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Taylor Law. Public Employee Relations. Summary of Plan to Prevent Strikes in Public Workers., 1968 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Taylor Law. Public Employee Relations. Drafts., 1968 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Taylor Law. Kkeel Testimony. Transcript of Hearing before New York State Joint Legislative Committee on Industrial and Labor Conditions., 1968 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Taylor Law. Statement by Kheel on Role of Legislative Bodies under the Taylor Law., 1969 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  September 25 1969
- James Barry Silver Documents, 1966-1981 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Corporation Agreement. St. George Hotel., 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Summary of Box Contents (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Strategies and Tactics of Collective Bargaining, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Transportation-Authority for Coordinating Transportation. Corporate and Correspondence., 1974 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Transportation. Center for Transportation Alternatives. Bylaws, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Transportation. Continuing Transportation Forum., 1973-1975 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Transportation. Financing Mass Transportation Brochure., 1972 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Transportation. Governor's Task Force on Public Authority., 1974-1975 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Transportation. In the Matter of Walt Whitman and Benjamin Franklin Bridge Tolls, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Transportation. Metropolitan Transportation Authority (MTA), 1975 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Transportation. Robert Moses Commentary. New Yorker., 1974 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Transportation. National Transportation Needs Study, 1971-1972 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Transportation. National Transportation Planning Manual, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Transportation. Port Authority of New York. History and Information., 1953-1974 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Transportation. Public Authority in New York State., 1974 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Transportation. Public Benefit Corporations in New York City., 1975 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Transportation. A Rational System of Bridge and Tunnel Tolls, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Transportation. Rational Transportation Magazine., 1974 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Transportation. Reports on Railroad Industry., 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Transportation. Court Case. St. Clair., 1972 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Transportation. Speeches by Kheel on Mass Transportation, 1971-1973 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Transportation. Statement by Kheel, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Transportation. Statement by Others., 1973 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Transportation. Statewide Public Authorities. Volume 1., 1972 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Transportation. Statewide Public Authorities. Volume 2., 1972 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Transportation. Transportation, City Size and Congestion Tolls. Lester B Lave., 1969 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  April 1969
- Task Force on Urban Development Corporations., 1974 (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Vice President Johnson. Report of Theodore Kheel on Equal Employment Opportunity., 1962 (Box 4, Folder 27)
- New York State Urban Development Corporation., 1971-1974 (Box 4, Folder 28)